Welcome in. This is The Operator
Economy. A series where we break down one
business you can build on your own. This
week... how Accenture made billions of dollars
doing something you can do from home. For
about a hundred bucks a month.
Last year, Accenture booked five point nine
billion dollars of GenAI. work. Billion with a
B. Not building AI. Installing it.
And that same service? At solo scale?
That's a two thousand dollar project. One operator.
One month.
Okay so here's the thesis. Every business out
there now knows it's supposed to be using
AI. Almost none of them know how. That
gap? Between knowing and doing? That's not a
mystery. That's a service business. And it's got
a name. It's called implementation. You're not building
models. You're not raising venture capital. None of
that. You're taking tools that already exist and
wiring them into how a real business
actually runs. Its intake. Its follow-ups. Its
reporting. I spent over a decade building products
for businesses of every kind. Hospitality,
retail, grocery, SaaS, B2B.
And the pattern was everywhere, every single time.
Technology that got bought, half installed, and
quietly abandoned. The gap was never the
software. It was the person who'd stand
there until it actually ran. And here's the
thing, the reason this is buildable by one
person now... is that the installation tools
went no-code.
What used to take a systems integrator and
six months? That's a workflow you can stand
up in an afternoon. Which raises the obvious
question, right?
If it's that easy...
why is Accenture out there charging billions for
it?
Okay so, start at the top of the
market. Because this is the part that proves
demand. Accenture's GenAI. bookings
roughly doubled. Five point nine billion
dollars, fiscal twenty twenty-five. That's
billion with a B. And revenue from that
work roughly tripled to two point seven billion.
But here's the detail that matters more. Their
overall new bookings? Flat. The
AI implementation work is the only thing
growing in that whole business. And by late
twenty twenty-five they just stopped reporting it
separately, because it was touching eighty percent of
their large deals. It stopped being a
category and started being the business. Now the
other end of the market. There's a reported
model making the rounds. A solo automation
agency, forty thousand dollars a month, five
clients, all on retainer.
And look, I wanna be careful here. That
number's coming from a creator-economy blog, not audited
books. So treat that as the ceiling story,
not the median. The floor is better documented,
because honestly, it's boring. Freelancers doing
AI automation work at five to six grand
a month, running on maybe twenty bucks of
tooling.
And the pricing converges across pretty
much every source I found.
Two to five thousand for a first project.
Five hundred to five thousand a month for
the retainer after that. One more structural signal,
from the enterprise side this time. About half
of these AI projects pull through additional data
and systems work. Services attach to
services. Your two grand install?
That becomes a relationship. It's not a
transaction anymore. Every install my
team ever did, and I mean every one,
surfaced three problems we weren't even hired to
fix. The reservation fix exposed the
inventory mess. The inventory fix
exposed the reporting mess. That's not
scope creep. That's the business model.
So the same business exists at three scales.
Accenture's billions. Boutique agencies'
reported six figures. And a freelancer's few
thousand a month. The service is identical.
The only thing that changes is who's buying.
Okay so let's talk about the stack, because
this is the part people overcomplicate. The whole
thing costs less than a hundred bucks a
month. Under a hundred. The brain is
Claude or ChatGPT, twenty to
forty dollars. That's your analysis, your drafts, and
increasingly...
the build itself. The runtime is n8n,
Make, or Zapier.
That's the thing that actually executes the workflow
for the client. And n8n self hosted is
close to free, which matters a lot when
you're quoting margins. Then the client facing layer.
Airtable or Notion. That's the dashboard
they log into, the thing they feel ownership
of. And here's the thing, this is the
part clients think they're paying for. So make
it clean. And Loom for async delivery.
Recorded walkthroughs instead of meetings. Every tool
here has a free tier. So your cost
of goods on a two grand project? Rounds
to zero. Which means the entire game is
finding that first client. And that's exactly where
most people get it backwards.
Okay, the playbook. Let's get into it. Week
one. Pick one vertical you've actually worked in.
Not "small businesses." That's too broad,
too generic. One industry whose problems you can
name from memory. Every source on this business
converges on the same point. Vertical focus.
Mine would be hotels and restaurants, because I
built for them for years and I can
name their intake problems in my sleep.
Yours is whatever industry you can argue with.
Weeks two to four. Build two or three
real case studies. Do them cheap or free
for businesses you already know. And before you
go "wait, free work?"... you're not
donating work. You're buying proof.
And proof is the only marketing this business
needs. Then you package it. A fixed
scope offer. One named problem, one price
somewhere between two and five grand, one
deadline. Businesses don't buy
"automation." Nobody wants automation,
that's not what they're looking for. They buy
"your missed calls get answered and booked." That's
the sentence and that's the solution. The first
client comes from your existing network. And that's
not a hack. That's the model. Operators buy
from operators. Your credibility from the industry you
left, that's the actual asset here. And after
the install, offer the retainer. Maintenance plus one
new workflow a month. Five hundred to a
few thousand, depending on scope. Remember the
attach effect. The first project is designed to
surface the second.
Okay, so. The honest math.
And look, if you'd rather work from this
than scribble notes right now, the free blueprint
linked below has every one of these numbers
with its source. All of them. Margins
are real. Your costs are tools under a
hundred bucks and your time. That's it. That's
how you get these ninety percent margin claims,
and directionally? They're right. But
here's the detail that matters more. A realistic
first year is two to eight grand a
month. Not forty. Those forty thousand
dollar stories? Marketing artifacts. From people selling
courses about this exact business. My estimate, by
the way. And I'm flagging it as one.
Three failure modes. This is a service business.
Revenue stops when you stop. Retainers soften
that, they don't cure it. At three to
five clients, losing one client is losing a
quarter of your income. Think about that for
a second. And every automation you install is
something you now maintain. Forever.
When the tools update, guess who's fixing it.
So what do you actually get from this
business? Diversification. Income that
isn't a paycheck. A skill stack that
compounds. And a client list that becomes
distribution for whatever you build next. That's the
trade.
Okay so, here's the thing. The full blueprint.
The offer templates, the stack setup, the case
study framework, every source. All free.
Link's below. If breakdowns like this are useful,
subscribe. That's it. That's the ask. And
until next time... stop waiting for permission.
Build it. Own it. Operate it.